All right.
Someone asked me a question on paper,
which was a very good way to ask.
And they said if I want to collect seeds
to see emptiness directly,
could I
meditate
and in my meditation I imagine I am
teaching the pen
or the two husbands in the kitchen to
people. That's great. That's fantastic.
Yeah.
Yeah, anything you daydream about like
when you're in high school and you want
to ask a girl out,
first you meditate about it, right?
Then over and over and over and finally
you
it pushes you to ask, okay? So if you
meditate about teaching
pen or two husbands, uh
that's great. Yeah.
You can make seeds. Yeah, powerful
seeds.
Because you are close to the
source of karma, which is the in inside
of the mind.
So maybe it's more powerful than
teaching it outside.
Cuz mental karma is uh more powerful,
okay?
All right, we're going to do some more
Nagarjuna.
Uh
when you're
get
in these two days when you're meditating
in your room,
don't be lazy, okay? Do the meditation.
Maybe I will check
through the window.
I do it, okay? I I walk around. I don't
look through the window, but I
I do walk around and
check that people are in their cabins
and stuff.
Uh
be a tough guy, okay? It's going to
hurt. It hurts sometimes, okay? When do
you make progress in yoga?
Is when you are shaking. People, I don't
know I always feel embarrassed
when I'm shaking in the yoga. There's
one pose, uh what do you call that?
Side plank.
What do you call it?
especially if I had three coffees
before.
And uh
then I feel embarrassed, you know. Oh,
people going to see the teacher is
shaking.
But that's when you make your progress
is when you're shaking. When your legs
hurt and your mind is tired and your
back is not so good and you're hungry
and you would rather watch a
cat video.
Uh
when it hurts a little bit, it's that's
when you make progress, okay?
And in yoga also, so don't avoid the
don't avoid it. Don't give up. Just
stay there, you know. I don't know.
Sometimes I just
in my mind I talk to the yoga teacher. I
say, "Okay,
just do anything you want. I don't care.
I'll just do it, okay? I I don't like
it.
And I'm shaking, but
lunch is close.
And before that is shavasana.
I could Okay, come on. Just do what you
want to do with me. I don't care, you
know. So, just be it's not like a tough
guy. It's just like you give up. Okay,
beat me up.
You know, it's okay. I'll be better
person.
You know, same with your legs in
meditation and your back, okay? Just
say, "Okay."
You know, it's going to hurt, all right?
And your legs are going to hurt and
you're going to be tired.
The minute you try to meditate, somebody
starts talking outside loud.
Last night
Don't talk. Don't talk. Don't talk loud.
Don't talk loud outside. Don't talk loud
outside. Don't talk loud. Don't talk.
Okay.
Uh
The valley is very uh
shaped like this. So, if you talk
across the way I can hear it in my
cabin, okay? Better than the person next
to you. I don't know why. It's a strange
valley, yeah. You She knows.
Okay, here we go.
So, you got to be a tough guy in your
yoga and you got to be a tough guy in
your meditation. Just tell your body
shut up.
Tell your shaky arms shut up, you know?
And you got to be tough this morning
during the guidance.
Because he will confuse you. And just
say, "I don't care if you confuse me.
I'm going to stay I'm going to try. I'm
still going to try, okay? My mind is
shaking, but
I will try, okay? All right.
Uh there's a cute uh I I mentioned it a
little bit the other day, the human
computer
was talking about it, but Chönyi Lama
and the Gyalwa they use a very strange
word
after they finish the three
reasons
why
the
elements and their results, okay, cannot
be connected, cannot be happening, okay?
I left you with uh molecules, right? I
left you with molecules.
There was a Buddhist molecule.
It should have uh how many atoms?
Eight.
Four are
elements, which means in this chapter
causes
and four are
products of products of the elements,
okay? So, in Buddhism
every molecule should have eight atoms.
Uh four of them are the four
elements.
There are different elements. There are
different sets of elements. There's
four, there's five, there's six.
Okay? So, uh
when they want to talk about the four
What's the What's the Sanskrit word for
element that we learned?
Buddha, okay? Buddha. Uh and uh
if you want to
say I'm talking about the four, I'm
talking about the four, sometimes you
can say the big Buddhas.
Cuz these four are the big
source of everything. All physical stuff
has these four, so they're they're the
big ones. They're the stars of the
Buddhas.
So we say sometimes Maha Buddha, okay?
Say Maha
Buddha, okay? So
Buddha can also mean spirit,
uh be a
bad one, okay? Uh it has different
meanings.
It can mean existence. So if you
if you're talking about Buddhas and you
want to make it clear you're talking
about the elements, you can say, "Oh,
I'm talking about the Maha Buddhas."
Cuz they're big. Why? They're
everywhere, they create everything. All
physical things, okay?
Then there are four uh
products
of those Buddhas, right? The objects of
your senses.
What you see, what you hear.
Oops.
Not what you hear, cuz that's in
Abhidharma that doesn't stay.
What you smell, what you taste, what you
feel.
And there's a nice uh piece in the first
Dalai Lama's Abhidharma commentary,
which I worked on for 12 years.
And in there he says uh it makes sense
that a atom
uh should have
four elements in it and then four
products in it.
Uh
because as far as elements,
it's kind of the things you experience
outside.
And then as far as products of the
elements, it's what creates your
senses. It's what you can taste, what
you can hear uh what you can smell, what
you can see, okay? So, it makes sense
that an atom in Buddhist Buddhist atom
should have half outside stuff and have
inside stuff, okay? Got it? It kind of
makes sense.
It's not crazy.
Half of that
molecule is kind of elements and half of
that molecule is things you can
experience, and that's kind of cool,
okay? That makes sense. First Dalai Lama
teaches it that way, okay?
Okay, then uh there's a cute thing
What was the Tibetan human computer?
Uh the yogi who understands
suchness.
I want to hear all three parts
for $0.
Cuz you already make got rich from me.
The yogi who knows suchness.
In Tibetan, in Tibetan.
Deny.
Rigpa.
Naljor. Yeah, say deny.
Naljor.
Uh big meditator who understands
emptiness, okay?
Deny means tatva, suchness, emptiness.
Rigpa means understand and
Naljor is the Tibetan word for yoga
master.
Yoga master, Naljor, okay?
Jigme Lingpa Yujamma.
The Yujamma is Naljor. Naljor ma, lady
yoga master, okay?
So,
they say they ask a question to the
other. It's kind of cool. Chönyi Lama
and the Garchen Rinpoche talking
together.
So, hey
Nagarjuna
like who's a yoga master? What's a yoga
master? They said, well
yoga, you know, they're into the
physical rupa, right? What's rupa?
They're into the physical body, you
know, they're studying the
in a gross way, they're studying muscles
and bones and angles and
Okay, in a more subtle way, they are
studying the
prana and the and the wind and the body
values inside the body, okay? They're
kind of focused on
physical
but what makes them a master?
You know, can they lift their foot over
their head?
Is that Is that What do you think
Nagarjuna says?
Yeah, they're a master if they
understand
the elements
and the products of the elements in
their own body.
And that makes them a yoga master. And
they understand
Listen, okay? They understand how the
elements cannot be making the physical
body.
They understand how the elements cannot
be making the physical body. The whole
Abhidharma presentation, all that
molecule stuff is ridiculous.
Okay? It doesn't have anything to do
with your yoga or your health, right? Or
your your what your body looks like.
What has to do with your body and your
health and what you look like?
Tonglen
Okay? All right, that's all. Forget the
Buddhas and the Mahabuddhas and
you know, you want to be a real yoga
master?
You know, it's not like how many
handstands you can I mean, that also
helps.
By the way, if you do all that stuff
well, the prana moves well and then you
can understand emptiness better, okay?
So, that's not crazy.
The physical stuff is not crazy.
But, it's interesting. It's very I don't
know. To me, I like it.
The Garjuna is so
I think he was a hippie.
And uh
I feel like that.
You know, he says, "Oh, you want to be a
yoga master? Yeah."
"Oh, you want to make your yoga perfect?
Yeah."
"You like you want to get the elements
to make strong,
you know, yeah. Okay, then just
check it out, man. Something weird's
going on.
What? There's some people do the yoga,
they hurt their neck, they can't do
anything their whole life.
There's some people do the yoga
and they look great.
What is that? You know, it's not fair.
There's all these guys on the subway in
New York. I used to hate them in the
morning.
They're eating chocolate bars and they
look perfect. You know, I'm like
Something's weird's going on, you know.
I feel like the Garjuna, you know.
Something weird's going on. They're
They're not have a green drink.
Godiva.
Okay? And they look great, you know.
Something's going on, okay? It's not the
elements
that cause strong body. It's the karma.
Okay, that's what the Garjuna's been
trying to say. He say, "You want to be a
yoga master?
Understand that. And then you're a yoga
master. Even if you have a little tummy,
okay?"
You're a yoga master.
Got it?
Okay, that's the Garjuna's definition of
a yoga master.
How do you say it in Tibetan? Deny. Rig
Bay. Nal Jor.
A yoga master who understands the
emptiness
of the elements and the and the sense
powers. They are not created by the
elements. They are by kindness.
They are created by taking care of other
people, okay?
Cool. Then you're a yoga master. You
still have to do your yoga every day.
I'm sorry.
And you still have to put try to put
your foot behind your head, okay?
Because it will help you understand the
emptiness.
Got it? The The prana will flow, okay?
So, I'm not saying
don't be a regular yoga master. I'm
saying
be a
super yoga master who does both. Got it?
Okay. All right.
Next thing.
Uh now, this is get
When you teach uh Nagarjuna's wisdom,
you have to have a lot of background
knowledge
of all the schools, okay? All the
Buddhist schools. And uh
you can't really understand his most
famous book if you don't have a strong
background in the other schools, okay?
Like I've seen people
who have no background in any schools
and they write long
explanations of Nagarjuna's wisdom. And
and I don't know why it just irritates
me. I'm like
you know, uh
Anyway, it's like trying to drive a car
on a highway at 100 mph
and you didn't drive a car before, okay?
Something like that. It seems crazy.
Anyway,
uh in this case today
we we reached a place uh
near the end of the
What chapter we in?
What chapter near the end of chapter
four, an investigation of the
parts of a person and because the first
part is the physical part and then we
get into the elements, right? Actually,
the next chapter is the investigation of
the elements, but it's a different set
of elements, okay?
Uh so, here we're almost to the end of
the chapter about the
What was it? Parts of the body,
especially rupa, especially the rupa.
And he says, uh
Nagarjuna, as I told you,
he says, "Okay, you got it.
You got it. You got all this stuff.
What really causes the healthy body when
you do yoga? It's because you did
tonglen for other people. It's because
you served other people.
It's not that uh elements are going to
make you healthy. It doesn't come that
way.
Because that's suspicious. It should be
investigated. There's something wrong
with it, okay?
Then he finished with the physical body,
right? What's he supposed to do next?
For $20, what's he supposed to do next?
Yeah, feeling. Damn. Oh, excuse me.
Damn.
20 bucks.
Yeah, my leaky bank account. Bank
account, he's my bank account leak.
Uh
just like
I don't know.
Okay.
Yeah, he should do feeling, then he
should do discrimination, then he should
do the other stuff, and then he should
do awareness. These are the five heaps,
skandha, right? Skandha.
But, it looks like he gets lazy.
He says, "Yeah, they're all the same.
Okay, let's go to the next chapter."
What's the next chapter? An
investigation of the
uh the other elements, okay?
Uh
He says, "Uh just just same way. Same
thing. Okay, got it?"
Then somebody comes. Now, this is really
weird, okay?
Nagarjuna is the master of weird, right?
Uh he lets a guy come before the end of
the chapter. The guardian had just said,
"Okay, look, I spent the whole chapter
on on your first skandha.
The rest are the same, you know, just
same idea. You you figure it out."
Okay? Then he should finish the chapter,
he should go on.
But he allows another guy to come.
He allows another guy to come. And that
guy
says, "I like your logic.
I like your logic.
I got one for you, Nagarjuna.
Uh that feeling, second heap,
uh
well, that one exists from its own side.
It's I didn't do anything, okay? The the
second heap
exists from its own side.
Therefore, the first heap exists from
its own side.
Same logic.
I'm just using your logic.
Got it?
It's very cute. Nagarjuna lets this guy
come. He should finish the chapter, go
on.
You know? But he's like,
"Well, what if somebody comes and says
the same thing to you that I just said
to him?
Oh, the rest are the same.
Got it?
Number heap number one is coming from
your seats.
Then I don't have to go through all the
other four, it's the same, okay? Then
the other guy says, "Well,
but the second heap, I happen to know it
doesn't come from you, it comes from its
own side. Therefore, the first heap also
comes from its own side. Ha!"
I can't got it.
Now,
this is really amazing, okay? It took me
a while.
If the second heap
does come from its own side, okay? I
didn't do anything.
Okay? Feeling, you know? If feeling
comes from its own side,
then is it logical
that the physical body also comes from
its own sign?
Yeah. We're using the same logic as
Nagarjuna. Got it? I'll repeat it.
The gardener said, "Your body comes from
Tonglen.
Your yoga comes from Tonglen. You want
to be a yoga master?
You want your body to react, respond to
yoga?
Then do Tonglen, okay? He said that.
It's not coming from
chemicals.
It's not coming from carbon.
It's not coming from breathing, etc.
etc. etc. It's coming from how nice are
you to the other people in the yoga
class.
Okay?
That's where the yoga is coming from.
You want to be a yoga master?
And then he says, "And I don't
Come on, I don't have to explain feeling
and everything else. That your mind, the
state of your mind.
Obviously, that's the same. Do Tonglen,
do Tonglen, do Tonglen, do Tonglen."
Okay?
Then the other guy says,
"Oh, I like your logic.
I happen to know
that heat number two, it comes
Wasn't my fault.
It just came.
You know, my husband yell at me, I feel
bad.
It come from him. Don't come from me.
Therefore,
with with your logic, Nagarjuna, since
feelings
don't come from me, but they come from
my husband. He makes me mad, right? We
say it in English.
He made me unhappy.
He made me unhappy. Everybody says that.
He made me unhappy, so I divorce him.
He made me unhappy.
So, according if my feelings are coming
from my husband, because my husband made
me unhappy, okay?
And it's not my feelings, okay? It's my
husband.
Everyone who got a divorce felt better,
right?
And they never got another divorce.
I think 90% of second marriages fail in
the United States. 65% of first
marriages fail in the United States.
Okay, anyway.
So, listen to the logic. He says, "I
like your logic, Nagarjuna. If it's true
about one skandha, it's true about all
the skandhas. Now, my husband made me
unhappy. Therefore, my feelings are
coming from him. They are not coming
from my seeds. Therefore, my physical
body is coming from my elements."
Second thing,
not from what I do, not from how I treat
people, okay?
My physical body is coming from how many
hours I spend working out.
Okay? That's where it's coming from. Got
it? That's the same as saying with
feelings what?
My
husband made me unhappy, and the weight
lifting made me strong.
Okay? The guy who's in the seat says,
"Bullshit and bullshit."
Okay?
And the other guy says, "No, no.
My husband made me unhappy. Therefore,
working out makes me strong."
He uses the same logic back to
Nagarjuna. "Now,
it gets deeper, okay?
If it's true that your husband made you
unhappy, then is it true that working
out gives you muscles?"
Yeah. Yeah, that's true. But Nagarjuna
says, "Bad logic."
And in Tibetan it's called ribpa gotum
for $50.
5 4 3 2 1 0. Yeah!
You got to do it fast with him.
Uh, ribpa gotum means parallel logic.
Parallel logic, okay?
If if your logic is correct, Nagarjuna,
what's Nagarjuna's logic? If the first
heat comes from how you treat other
people, then I the other heats are the
same, okay?
Then parallel logic, Rinpoche Gotama,
if my husband can make me unhappy,
then weightlifting can make me handsome,
okay? Got it?
Same logic. Same Same thing.
Okay? Got it?
Then Nagarjuna says, "Your logic is bad.
My logic is good. They are not
parallel."
Then, you know,
if you're reading this 2,000-year-old
book, you're like,
"Must be a carving mistake.
Must Must be they put not when it's
supposed to be is."
Which we had yesterday, okay? We had it
in the carving. Must be a carving
problem.
Because Nagarjuna would never say,
"I can use that logic, but you cannot
use that logic." Got it?
He would never say that. The rules of
logic
are
one way for me and different for you.
Okay? You can't use the logic
that the other four heats are the same
if one of them is one way. You can't say
that. But you just said that. You just
used that logical method.
Okay? If it's true of one, it's true of
the other four. Nagarjuna, how come I
can't use the logic that you just used?
Okay? Nagarjuna does not attack
the statement.
He doesn't say,
"You know, your husband cannot make you
unhappy." He doesn't say that. He says,
"You can't use that logic that I just
used."
Okay? Now, if you're a translator or
you're a Buddhist,
you have to stop.
Don't blame it on the carving, okay?
Don't say, "Oh, there must be a carving
mistake. Let's go on to the next
chapter. We're so close to the next
chapter.
Let's just leave it."
I was very tempted, you know.
Like,
we really should move on, you know.
Can't spend too much time on this
chapter. But, I'm like, this bugs me.
This really bugs me, okay?
Then he says an interesting thing. He
says, uh okay, for this to understand
this one, you have to understand the
second school of Buddhism, which is
Sautrantika, which means they like
sutras.
They like sutras.
Okay? This The first school is basically
Abhidharma.
The second school is Sutrists,
the people who like sutras. For $20, why
are they called that?
Yeah, why? Tell me about the history of
the Abhidharma.
Come on, come on. You got You just gave
a $10 answer to a $20 question.
Yeah.
Three big meetings actually.
Great great explanation. So, what he
said was, I'll repeat it cuz maybe you
couldn't hear in the back.
Uh
after the Buddha passed away,
they had three meetings, okay? It took
hundreds of years. And the best
students, 500 arhats supposed to be,
they got together and they said, "What
do you remember?"
"Oh, I remember he talked about the
elements, you know." "What do you
remember?" "Oh, he talked about the four
products of the elements, you know." And
they all compared,
"Oh, do remember the molecule thing? I I
don't remember. How much? Seven or
eight? Where's the Where's the sound?
No, he said, you know, and they argued
and they
they made the Abhidharma. Abhidharma is
not a sutra.
The Abhidharma
is the result
of big meetings, which is always a
disaster.
Many people's opinion
compromise
you know, it never works. I like
dictatorship.
The Lama says what to do.
And everybody says, yes, sir.
Not really.
Uh
anyway,
so
the another school came
called the Sutrist and they say, look,
let's stick to the original statements
of the Buddha. Let's stick to the Heart
Sutra Dharma. Let's Well, they don't
believe that, but let's stick to the
basic sutras.
We don't believe the notes that you took
and you put them together into
Abhidharma. Abhidharma is the notes of
the main students. And that this second
school says,
we don't want to read the notes. We want
to read the original. We want to hear
the video.
We want to hear the original video. We
don't want to read somebody's notes. By
the way, the notes that were printed for
SCI courses from 19
93 etc., they are not clean. They are
not always correct, so just be careful
with them.
The guy who made the website took the
notes. Understand?
So, he put the notes in there and
they're 80% good, but there's some
mistakes, okay? And I don't have time to
to do them all, okay?
So,
Sutrist schools started to enjoy logic,
okay? Logic and perception theory. How
do you see things
with your mind that you cannot see with
your eyes. Okay? That's there They are
very interested about this question. How
do you use a third eye?
Okay? How do you see things
with logic that you cannot see with your
eyes or your nose or your tongue, okay?
And they got very interested in this
question. And And they say,
you know, you don't need secret
Buddhism. You need a third eye.
You study
how to make logic airtight.
How to make correct logic.
And then then you can see everything in
the universe, okay? Like Einstein, he
figured out that the bomb should work
before he made the bomb. That's all.
Then he went to the president Roosevelt
and said, "I can do it." And Roosevelt
said, "Where Where is it?" And he said,
"It's here."
That's logic. He used logic.
Unfortunately, he
he used logic, okay? I heard a
terrible thing uh
So, they blew up the first one near here
in New Mexico. You can see New Mexico.
Those mountains that way are New Mexico.
And the place where they blew up the
first bomb is not that far.
And uh so, they're all ready to blow up
the first bomb. And um Roosevelt's like,
"Uh is this safe? Is everything safe?"
They said, "Oh, no problem, you know."
"Could anything happen?" "Well, there's
a little chance
that all the oxygen in the world will be
ignited."
Which means the whole world will burn.
But we think it's not going to happen.
Yeah.
Let's check. You know, this is a real
scientist, you know? They don't care if
they burn up the whole world including
themselves. They're like, "Let's check."
Then they blew up the you know.
Why am I talking about that?
They use logic to see things that you
can't see with your eyes. That's the
specialty of the second school who are
the guys who like the sutras and they're
not crazy about the the notes of the
senior students, okay? Notes of the
senior students is one school.
Abhidharma, okay? And then sutras guys
who say, "No, let's stick to the
sutras."
Okay?
And they like logic cuz they can use
logic to see things you can't see with
your eyes, okay? Now,
typical syllogism, logical statement.
Logical statement has four parts.
Logical statement has four parts, okay?
I'm not going to teach you logic.
By the way, if you're going to be a ACI
teacher,
there's a trick I will teach you.
When the audience, like in Singapore,
heard the pen 3,000 times already, you
can say, "Don't worry, I'm not going to
teach you the pen tonight."
I'm I'm not going to talk about,
you know, how it comes,
you know, how the dog looks at it.
I'm not going to go into that, okay? How
the human sees it different. I'm I'm not
going into that, how it's produced by a
picture, you know, let's just leave it
tonight, you know, how different people
see different things cuz you have
picture, you know.
And I'm just teaching you a trick, okay?
So, I'm not going to teach you logic.
Cuz it's boring and it's difficult, but
every logical statement
has four parts. Every logical statement
has four parts and the English word for
logical statement is syllogism, okay?
And it doesn't pass the waiter test.
What's the waiter test, Geshe Michael?
Good.
I'll repeat it. You You want to repeat
it?
Repeat it.
Now, the question is in the translation
team
uh in China and in America called mixed
nuts, pure gold mixed nuts.
What do we mean when we say
that word doesn't pass the waiter test?
Yeah. So, go to the Mexican restaurant
in Wilcox, okay, on your day off.
Go to the Mexican restaurant. There's a
little Mexican restaurant.
And they say, "What would you like to
order?" And say, "I would like a
syllogism."
And then see what they say, okay? See
what they say.
You know?
If they go like this, huh?
What?
What language is that?
Don't use the word in your teaching,
okay? Try to use words in your teaching
that everyone understands, okay? So,
logical statement, which is a syllogism,
should have four parts. Number one,
what thing are you talking about, okay?
What thing are you
talking about?
The physical body, the first skandha,
okay? That's my first part of my
syllogism, okay? Let's talk about your
physical body, okay?
Let's talk about your physical body,
okay? Number two,
it is coming from
elements,
chemicals,
energies in the body, okay? It is coming
from elements, chemicals,
energies in the body, okay?
It is not coming from how you treat
other people, okay? Got it? That's the
other guy.
That's the other guy, right? Take your
physical feeling or I'm sorry, cancel
that.
The example is take your feelings, okay?
Take it Okay, I'm going to change the
example.
Number one, take your feelings.
Number two, I'm sorry.
It is your physical body, okay? Number
one, let's take your physical body,
okay? It's not coming from how you treat
poor people, okay? It's coming from how
many vitamins you eat, you know, do you
drink green drinks? That's where your
physical body's coming from.
That's his statement, okay? That's what
he's trying to prove. The second part
is called what he's trying to prove
about the subject, okay? About the first
one, okay? First one is what?
Let's take your physical body. And
what's the statement he's trying to
prove?
It doesn't come from how you treat poor
people. It doesn't come from giving food
to hungry people. It does not. It comes
from how many green drinks you have, uh
how much chocolate you can avoid.
Okay, it's the
It's coming from its own side, okay? Got
it?
That's his
statement he's trying to prove.
Does the other person By the way, who's
talking this statement?
Who's talking this statement?
Yeah, the other guy, the anti Nagarjuna
guy. Who's listening to the guy?
Nagarjuna. Good, I Nagarjuna. So, he
says, "Look, Nagarjuna, let's take your
body, okay?
You think it comes from
how you feed poor people
and not from yoga, but you are wrong.
You are wrong, okay? It comes from yoga.
It comes from how many green drinks you
have, okay? That's where it comes from.
Got it?
By the way, that's why we have green
stretch
pen.
Because the pen explains the green and
the stretch.
Right? Okay.
So, Nagarjuna doesn't believe what the
guy said. Your body is coming from your
vitamins and your green drinks and your
yoga, okay?
Then, the guy's going to give a reason.
Ready? The guy's going to give a reason.
Here's the guy's reason. And he's just
following Nagarjuna's method.
What's the reason for $50?
What's the guy's reason, Daniel, for
$50?
Yeah, it's the same as your feelings.
$50 for Daniel. He's going to split it
with me.
Just kidding.
Got it? Here's the guy's statement,
number one. Let's take your physical
body, Nagarjuna. Number two, it does not
come from feeding other people. It comes
from how much yoga you do and many how
many green drinks you drink, okay?
Number three, what's his reason?
It's just like your feelings. It's just
like your feelings and we know your
feelings come from other people. My
husband made me unhappy.
Okay, got it?
It Look, it's just the same.
And And you can't say I'm wrong because
of you just said the other four heaps
are the same as the body.
I'm using your system of logic. Got it?
At the end of the chapter, Nagarjuna
said, "I don't have to explain the other
four heaps. Why? I taught you the first
one, the other four is the same." Okay,
Nagarjuna. My feeling comes from my
husband.
Therefore, my body comes from vitamins.
Same logic. Same logic as you.
Got it?
And then, by the way, the fourth part of
the syllogism
is normally
uh
you say it's like
and then you say something. Okay? Now,
this guy already used that
in the first three, but normally
you say it's like your mind or it's like
your discrimination. It's like heap
number three or it's like heap number
five.
Okay, don't Let's not worry about it.
Now,
the guardianess says, "I don't allow you
to use the same logical system that I
used."
Okay? I said, "The other four heaps are
the same."
But you can't do that.
Is that fair?
No, it's not fair.
Okay? It's not fair. Okay? Now, listen.
Okay? Are you still with me?
Okay. It's illegal in a logical
statement
to use the same thing in position number
two and in position number three. Okay?
That's called husband or wife logic.
We should go
to the good-tasting restaurant
because it's a good-tasting restaurant.
Okay?
Do you want to go the Japanese
restaurant tonight, honey? No.
Where do you want to go? Italian
restaurant. Why? I like it.
Okay?
We should go The Italian restaurant has
good food because it has good food.
Okay? That's illegal. Illegal logic.
Okay? Got it?
And that's usually why a fight starts
between a couple in a couple. Somebody
uses this logic. Okay?
We should go to the Italian restaurant
cuz the food's good. Well, why? Well,
cuz the food's good.
Okay, they don't say cuz I like the food
and you don't like the food. They don't
They don't say that.
That's That's logical, right?
To repeat the sec- the third To repeat
the second thing
in the third position is illegal. For
$300,
why is it relevant here?
7 Who's Kevin Caney? No, he's not. 6
2 1 0. Yay!
Is there any way Who said that?
No, people in the box can't answer. No,
people who just made money can't answer.
You don't know that?
I'm changing the rules halfway.
I'm following the Gardena's example.
Well, what what what did you want to
say?
You don't have to prove anything.
No.
Now,
listen.
The Gardena is accusing the other guy,
"You just said the same thing in
position three that you said in position
two. Your logic is illegal."
What did the other guy say?
Let's take your physical body, Gardena.
It's coming from green drinks and yoga.
Uh
because my husband made me unhappy.
Okay.
Got it?
Now, listen.
The other guy
believes that the thing in the second
position
is like the body that comes from
vitamins and green drinks.
And the other guy believes
that the feeling,
the statement about the feeling is
coming from its own side.
Got it?
Okay, I'll say it again.
The other guy believes that his words
that he used in position two
have power from their own side.
And he believes that the words he used
as a reason have power from their own
side. He's using the same thing.
I'll say it again.
It's like when you're talking to your
wife, "I already told you.
I already told you."
Does the wife always understand? No.
Do words have power from their own side
like green drinks do?
No, they don't. But that guy believes
they do. Therefore, his second statement
and his third statement are the same.
Got it? It doesn't matter what he's
talking about. It he could say because
fish fly.
It doesn't matter what he says. If he
believes
that words have the power to give
understanding, he's mistaken.
Okay? And he has the same idea about
position two.
And he has the same idea about position
three.
And he is illegally repeating the same
thing in position two and position three
because what he's really saying is my
words have the power to prove what I
want to prove.
And that's wrong.
It any married person can tell you.
Any married person can tell you, okay?
You feel like I I explained everything
to you. The Italian restaurant has good
desserts.
The waitresses are cool.
It's cheap. Okay, you understand? We
should go to the Italian restaurant. I
want to go to Japanese.
You know, and then you feel like your
words should have the power to make your
wife understand, but they don't.
Because words are also coming from the
listener.
What you hear is coming from you. If you
don't understand my class, that's your
fault.
Got it?
Same as a wife. Same as a wife. Now,
I'll say it one more time, okay?
It's illegal to say
uh
take the Italian restaurant. It has good
food because
it has good food. Okay, that's not
logic. That's not You cannot repeat as
the proof the thing you're trying to
prove. You cannot. It's illegal.
Did the guy do it? Did the other guy do
it? Did he break the rule of logic? I'll
tell you what he said.
He said, "Take your body.
It's coming from green drinks and yoga.
It's condition
is coming from green drinks and yoga
because your husband makes you upset.
Your husband makes you unhappy.
Got it?
If it's true
that your husband can make you unhappy,
then it is logical that green drinks can
make you healthy. Skanda two, skanda
one.
Got it?
If it's true, that's okay. It's good
logic, okay? But
now listen.
He believes that his words have a power
to make you understand
no matter what your karma is.
Okay? Got it? He doesn't understand that
whether you understand me is coming from
you. It's not coming from Geshe
Michael's words. I can use a thousand
different words. I can teach you
200 kinds of logic,
but it's not going to work if you don't
have the karma, okay?
The power of understanding what I'm
saying isn't coming from me. It's not
coming from my words. And the power to
be strong is not coming from green
drinks.
And the feelings you have are not
created by your husband.
Your husband cannot make you unhappy.
Okay, got it?
Got it?
So, the same mistake he made in position
number two,
and the same mistake he made in position
number three,
he's making in his logic.
Because he thinks his logic should work
from its own side, no matter what your
karma.
Got it? He thinks words have power of
their own, but they don't, do they?
Half the people in this room are totally
confused. Half the people have the
peepee. The rest of the people don't
care.
Okay. No, I'm just kidding.
So,
got it? It doesn't matter what you say.
The power is not in the words.
Okay? When he says to Nagarjuna,
"Your body is coming from green drinks
because your husband can make you
unhappy."
He thinks his words have power inside
them, Atman power, like aspirin. Okay,
got it?
So, he's repeating the same mistake with
two and three.
It's very subtle. It's very, very
subtle, okay?
So, cook it, okay?
Cook it. It's extremely difficult. It's
extremely difficult, and we're going to
go deeper
tomorrow. So, think about it this
afternoon.
There was a guy named Edgar Cayce
100 years ago.
He
American mystic.
You know, like he would tell the future
or
and his system, he would take the book
and put it under his pillow
and then he would sleep.
And when he woke up, he understood the
whole book. You understand what I'm
saying?
You can try.
Okay, just put your reading Nagarjuna
reading under your pillow
take a good nap
and then maybe you understand what the
hell is he talking about.
Okay.
What time am I supposed to go to?
Okay, do I have more time or not?
Do we go to 10:30 or 9:30?
Oh, I'm sorry. Let's take a pee pee
break, okay?
And we'll come back and we'll go deeper
into this thing you already don't
understand.
All right, okay.
Okay.
I want to take you a little bit deeper
about that last thing, okay?
So, if you're already lost
sometimes if you get more lost, you find
your way.
You know.
One time I got lost walking back here. I
couldn't find my way back and uh
you just keep walking around.
You find a place. But be careful
walking. Sometimes when you walk up far
far away, everything looks the same, you
know, you don't remember
where is your house, okay? So, be
careful. Don't lose sight of the house,
okay? Or somebody's house, okay?
All right.
So, something happened after Nagarjuna,
okay? Something happened after
Nagarjuna. The accountants took over for
700 years before Nagarjuna, right?
Then Nagarjuna came and cleaned
everything up and you know what happens
when you clean your house.
Then somebody comes in and mess it up,
right? It's the same with philosophy.
With Buddhism. So, after Nagarjuna,
uh there came a very famous
Buddhist called Buddhapalita. Okay,
Buddhapalita. And uh it means like
protector of the Buddha or something.
Palita.
Uh
and so Buddhapalita came
and he wrote a explanation of this book.
Many, many people tried to explain this
book because it's so difficult. So,
Buddhapalita wrote a explanation maybe
500 years after Since 500 AD, so 300
years after Nagarjuna.
Buddhapalita wrote a book.
Uh that book name is for $10.
Buddhapalita. You Iyah.
$10 to the young man.
Uh
Yeah, everybody calls It's like if John
wrote the book and they call the book
John. Okay, that's what happened.
So, Buddhapalita wrote the book
and after that everybody calls the book
Buddhapalita. I don't know why cuz the
book and the person are different,
right? But
uh
Then he wrote a good book. It's a good
book. It's a good explanation. Okay, not
bad. Okay, pretty basic but good. Okay.
Especially, he liked to explain the
logic
about four choices.
Do Where do things
come from? Where does the tree
come from? Okay, where does the tree
come from?
And Nagarjuna gave us four choices.
Okay, I don't know if you remember. It
was a long time ago.
He gave us four choices. These are very,
very famous Buddhist explanation of
emptiness. Very, very famous. It's
called the four choices, okay? The four
choices. It's one of the famous proofs
for emptiness, okay? Number one.
Does a tree come from itself, okay?
Does the tree grow from itself, okay?
Number two.
What?
Does the tree grow from something else,
like a
seed, okay?
Choice number three. Does a tree come
from
both
uh the tree and the seed together?
And number four, most crazy one.
Does the tree just poop and the tree's
there, no cause, okay? Without a cause,
okay?
And when you teach it, which you maybe
you have to do someday,
uh
I don't know. Most people will go to the
easy ones first and then go to the
difficult one, okay? So, uh you know,
and even the garden is like, okay, look.
Number one is easy. I mean, tree doesn't
come from a tree cuz when the tree's
growing, the tree's not there yet, so
how could a tree come from itself? I
mean, that's crazy. That's That's crazy,
right?
Then, uh how could a tree number four,
how could a tree come with
no cause? I mean, that's also crazy, you
know, just pop up, you know, not
possible.
You know, then both come from itself and
from something else. If it doesn't come
from itself, then it can't come from
both itself and something else. That's
also impossible. Those three are easy.
The difficult one is number
two. Does a tree come from a seed, okay?
Does a tree come from a seed? And the
garden says
no.
Okay? No, okay? Now, and Buddha Palita
explained it pretty good. Okay.
Then came a troublemaker
named Bob Viveka. Too many V's in his
name. His mother should have taken one
or two out.
He should be Bob A or
Okay. I I hate this name.
Bob Viveka. Three V's, okay? Bob Say Bob
A.
Viveka.
And it means Viveka is in Sanskrit. I
mean, it's a yoga word also. It means
that he's very good at figuring out
things.
Viveka means like Vivekananda.
Was it the famous yogi who came to the
United States? What's his name?
Was it Vivekananda?
A what?
Yeah, Vivekananda. Came to the world's
fair in Chicago in 1890 or something.
Brought yoga to the United States. Uh
Anyway, the name means
they have a good ability to figure
things out. Okay.
So, his name is Mr. Figure Things Out
pretty good. Bob A Viveka. Okay.
And he really does.
But, he gave a famous bad suggestion,
just like your mother-in-law.
Okay. He gave a very famous bad
suggestion. $50.
Which one?
More. I need more information.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Now, should I give him
50 when I have to give him so many
clues?
35.
Okay. He said,
"You can't say, okay? He suggested to to
Buddhapalita,
'Don't say it like that.
Don't say things don't come from
themselves, things don't come from
something else, things don't come from
both, and things don't come without a
cause. Don't say it that way because the
second one is correct.
Things do come from other things. You
see? Don't say it that way. I have a
suggestion. Let's improve Nagarjuna,
which is always a
bad suggestion.
Let's fix Nagarjuna.
Let's add something to the second one,
which is what? Things don't come from
other things
really self-existently
without What do you call that? I didn't
do anything.
Okay? You should say
things don't come from other things
without I didn't do anything. With I
didn't do anything.
You always did something. It's always
your fault. Okay, got it? Your wife is
correct.
Everything is your fault.
Okay? Got it? So, Bhavaviveka said, "We
should add the word
uh really come from really or
self-existently or from its own side or
I didn't do anythingly. I didn't do
anythingly.
Okay? All right? We should add some
words there. Okay?
Then came Chandrakirti. Okay? Then
shortly after that, I don't know.
By the way, Bhavaviveka's around 550,
550 AD.
Uh Chandrakirti's like 100 years later.
Some people say at the same time as
Bhavaviveka, and he said, "I don't like
your addition.
I don't like you fixing Nagarjuna. He
don't need it.
Nagarjuna knew what he's talking about.
And Buddha Viveka says, "No,
you have to add that word, otherwise it
doesn't make sense. Things do come from
other things. Got it?"
He said, "You have to add those words,
by themselves, from their own side,
without your karma, without, you know, I
didn't do anything, okay? You have to
add those words, okay?"
$100.
There's only one person that has a
chance in this room.
What did Chandrakirti say
to Buddha Viveka? Okay, hold on, hold
on, hold on, hold on.
100 bucks. Man, I'm losing money.
I need worse students. Bring some worse
students.
Cheaper students.
He said that Buddha Viveka was
thinking that the really had the
self-existing power of explaining.
Oh, I bow DOWN TO YOU.
PERFECT.
PERFECT, OKAY?
NOW, we already said things don't come
from something else.
Okay? And maybe did the other guy
understand or not? We don't know, okay?
What we mean is by themselves, right? We
mean that.
Okay, got it?
So, when we say you have to add some
words,
it means, got ready? It means you
believe the words you added have a power
of their own, but you don't believe the
words that Nagarjuna started with have a
power of their own. You're crazy.
You're crazy, okay? If if Nagarjuna's
word
had power of its own, if they come from
their own side, like the I didn't do
anything husband, okay?
Then you don't need to add other words,
okay? They have their own power.
No, but we have to add these words.
People will understand it if we add
these words. Listen, if they didn't
understand the words in the first place,
they won't understand the words when you
add them because the second words are
not more powerful than the first words.
Cuz they don't also come from their own
side. And that's what we're talking
about anyway.
Got it?
Where did we hear this argument before?
Like yeah, before this moonies.
It's exactly when the guy in the garden
said to the other guy, "Got it?"
So, historically, hysterically,
uh
the other guy that the guy in the garden
is talking to made a mistake. He thinks
the words have their own power.
300 years later, it came up again, okay?
Bob Viveka said, "We have to add some
words."
Why? The words we add, everyone will
understand. The words we didn't add to,
they are not everyone can understand.
Got it? It's illogical, okay? It's
illogical.
It's like this, okay? Watch.
Fourth possibilities.
Things don't come from themself. The
tree doesn't come from the tree.
The tree doesn't come from the tree and
the seed. Number three.
The tree can't come with nothing, okay?
And the tree doesn't come from the seed.
That mean in English that means I'm
making a joke.
Got it? You understand?
Of course they come from seed, but not
by themself, okay? The seed doesn't have
the power.
The tree will grow from the seeds if you
shared shade with other people.
Your crops will grow.
The rain will come,
the soil will be good.
The hot weather will come at the right
time
if you feed other people. It doesn't
depend on the sun or the soil or the
seed, okay? Got it?
Okay? So,
he said to Bhavaviveka, you
you already broke the statement of
Nagarjuna. If you want to add words, you
you don't understand. You already don't
understand, okay? Historically,
uh the same problem happened that we
just talked about with the three parts
of a logical statement, okay?
Historically, it's a very famous uh
problem, okay? Did you have a question,
Mr. Myrtle?
But if that is true, then we don't need
the DCI or the ACI or any explanation
because it always depends on the karma
of that a person. We don't have to say
anything.
It's absolutely true.
Let's all just relax.
No, it's true. It is true.
If if it's true that Bhavaviveka doesn't
have to add words, then it's true that
Nagarjuna didn't have to make arguments.
He should have retired before he
started.
No, it's also true. It is true.
Okay? We we add words
in the hope that the person's karma will
ripen
about the second words, but not about
the first words. But when Bhavaviveka
added words, he didn't understand that.
That's all.
Okay? That's all. That's all.
I'm I'm adding words right now.
I'm doing it myself.
Uh
but I understand that if you understand,
it's going to come from whether you
share what you understand with other
people.
I understand that. So, I'm adding words
and I'm encouraging you to teach. It's a
teacher
training, okay? So, I'm hoping
you will collect the karma to understand
my words, and that's why I'm still
talking
instead of going home to take my nap,
which 66-year-old people like to do.
Okay? Understand? Okay? Yeah, good
point. It's a good point. Okay, good.
Uh
But, Baba Vivek did not give up his
opinion. Okay?
He kept saying,
"My added words,
the words I want to add,
really come from other thing. Okay?
Really come from other thing. They have
a independent power
that the guardian's words don't have.
Okay? And the really, especially if you
say it with the voice, "Really?" "They
really come from this now." That has a
power. That has a special power, and
that power is independent. That power
exist in the word, especially if you
say,
"I didn't do anything."
You have to say it like that. Practice.
Everybody, 1 2 3. "I didn't do anything.
My husband yelled at me."
Okay?
Why am I making you do it? Because you
do it every day a thousand times.
Okay? That's what this class is about.
Shut up and stop blaming on your
husband.
Okay? Got it? But, when you get out of
this class, you'll do the same thing,
and so will I. Okay.
Everything's Veronica's fault.
Except the things that are Jigme's
fault.
Right?
Okay.
Uh
So, the words, especially if you do it
right, really
uh they have a independent power. Why is
that word important?
Okay, come on. Louder, louder.
Yeah.
That started a whole school
of middle way, which is lower school,
middle way, called
Svatantrika, which means
independent school. Now you know why.
Now you know why, okay? The lower
middle way school
got the name
independent because of what?
Really? No. Really? Okay. Really? If you
do your use your hands and your voice,
really?
Then that has independent power. That
has independent power.
Our logic has independent power. Did you
hear that before?
Yeah, the guy here. The guy The guy who
was fighting those people 300 years
before that, and they came back
as Bobby Maybe they were reborn as Bobby
Vivek.
And they came back with the same stupid
argument. You got to add really. You got
to say really. Why? Really has a power
that it doesn't come from other things
doesn't have.
It has independent power.
You're so stupid. I'm going to call you
independent school.
Okay. Lower school, lower middle way.
So Bobby Vivek is the big gun of the
lower middle way school, and they are
called independent partly because they
think really has independent power.
And if you're going to talk to your
husband, you have to
you know, use your hands and your
shoulders and
that's the only way husbands can
understand because this has a power
Yelling has a power that talking softly
doesn't have.
Really?
This has independent power.
So you have with the husband, with a
man, that the little thick here, thick
then you have to you have to use your
hands and you have to go and you have to
talk louder, okay? That has an
independent power
that reasonable, calm discussion doesn't
have.
Okay, got it?
Who's the big gun of the higher middle
way?
Nagarjuna. Nagarjuna, okay? He's the
hero.
He's the leader of the higher middle
way, okay? Who's his general?
Chandrakirti
and Sucandra.
Okay?
Got it?
Okay, we finished that.
What's the next Okay, we're moving on to
the What has my time? Oh, perfect. Okay.
Maybe I'll let you out early so you can
meditate longer.
Or we could add extra yoga. Who's doing
the yoga today?
Is it a family thing to make the
to make the students suffer?
Maybe I can think of something else to
say.
I got it. Okay.
We're going to go to the fifth chapter,
okay? We're done. Now, my style in this
week is hopefully at the end of the
class, I'll give you a taste of the next
chapter, okay? I'm I'm not on time. I'm
one day behind already.
25% behind already, but
I want to give you a little taste of the
next chapter. It's a It's a method of
teaching
that you might consider yourself when
you teach.
Uh think about
giving them a little taste of the next
class. And then
we say it gives continuity to the whole
program, okay? So I'm going to We're
going to go to the fifth chapter store
and take a little bite of the ice cream.
There, okay? Just to get you in the
mood. And then
we'll we'll work on it tomorrow. Okay,
got it? So, here's the fifth chapter.
What's it called?
An investigation of the elements. Now,
listen.
The English word element has two
different Sanskrit words.
Or at least, okay?
All right? As the four elements,
probably you should say bhuta, okay? You
learned that word already, okay?
But, his fifth chapter,
he's going to a different set of
elements, and that word is dhatu, dhatu,
okay? Dhatu, okay? Dhatu.
Set set
Okay, the the root Do you have it there,
Tim? I don't know. You got it there
somewhere.
I'll teach you a Sanskrit word. It might
be on your quiz.
It might not be on your quiz.
If you don't finish your quiz, it
doesn't matter.
Okay.
Yeah, and there you go. Okay, the
meaning is element.
So, we can say pancha dhatu means five
elements, okay? Not four. Four is
bhuta, bhuta, okay? Five is different.
Dhatu is different. Five dhatus, okay?
The Tibetanese what? Human dictionary?
Come. Yeah.
And it also means category. When you
divide
the human being
into 18 parts, it's also called dhatu,
okay? It's also called dhatu. So, dhatu
means
Uh the root is the the verb dha. Say
dha.
Which means to put something or to set
something. And cognates are
to do or to did or deed, fact.
D H can change the F, okay?
And factory, okay? It just means real
thing.
Set down in stone.
Okay? Taha, okay? Dhatu. So, dhatu means
like
basic building block of reality, okay?
Basic building block of reality is
called dhatu. And that's the
subject of chapter five, okay? We're
going to do how many chapters this term?
Om mani padme hum, inshallah. Om mani
padme inshallah.
Okay.
We're going to do six chapters. So, this
now when we hit the fifth chapter, we're
halfway through.
Okay? Three, four, and five, okay? Five
is called an investigation of the
dhatus.
You can misunderstand it and and think
he's talking about the 18. He's not.
He's talking about five, okay? Which is
very similar to the elements, okay? You
just add
space, okay? Sa chu men long nam kha.
Prthivi
ap
tejas
vayu
akasha
space
Okay? Here we go again. Prthivi
ap
tejas
vayu
akasha akasha, okay? Akasha, okay.
All right. So, we're going to go to the
new chapter.
And your homework question, which is the
last homework question on number three,
which I'm exactly one homework behind.
Uh
and these homeworks take about seven or
eight hours to write, okay? It's hard
and I don't have much time.
Cuz people want to talk to me.
But that's okay. All right. Uh
Which of the five elements
does he choose to talk about first?
These are the four, by the way.
You have to add the space. Okay, we have
to add space.
a.k.a. a s h a akasha
a
Uh don't put namkha.
Put the Sanskrit Oh, sorry. You're
right. n a m
space m k h a apostrophe m k h a
apostrophe for the Tibetan, okay?
In many languages, kha means empty
space.
This is called kha in Tibetan.
Okay.
There you go. Okay, the Sanskrit is
akasha.
And the Tibetan is namkha, okay?
I was tempted to do the four spaces
meditation.
Uh well, I think it might give you
indigestion.
Okay, I think I'll focus on the two that
we have, the lines dance and
tonglen and maybe joining them, okay?
All right. So,
the arya chooses space.
Okay, he could have chosen earth, water,
fire, wind, or space, but he chooses to
talk about space. Why?
It's weird.
It's difficult. It's difficult, okay?
When he did the five skandhas, he did
the most
simple one first.
Then the next chapter, when he does the
five elements, he says, "Let's go
deeper.
Let's talk about the most difficult one,
which is space, because it acts
different than the other four.
It acts different than the other four.
And we're going to talk about it, okay?
Now, your homework question has two
parts.
It says, uh,
which of the elements does he choose to
examine first, which is
space, akasha, okay?
And what method does he use to
investigate it? What method does he use
to investigate it? And he does ten sun.
Ten sun. Say ten sun.
Ten sun.
And you're going to be sorry
about it
cuz it's extremely difficult. He
Okay? He He doesn't just look into
space.
He looks into ten sun of space.
Human dictionary?
I'll give you a clue. It comes from
Adam's text.
Hm?
Close.
Uh, you have to pay me.
Say
ten yi.
Ten yi.
Ten ja.
And this is a big Buddhist subject, and
it's difficult. But if you if I don't
teach you a little bit about it,
you cannot read this chapter.
Okay? If you don't know the other
schools, you can't read this book, okay?
So, this is a big idea
from the second school. Who's that?
By the way, they're also nerds, right?
Logician.
Definitely nerd.
Okay? Got it? Abhidharma, logician, both
nerds, okay? That's all. The two lower
schools.
Hinayana nerds, okay?
Then let's talk about logic. Let's talk
about logic. What do you want to talk
about? Let's talk about syllogisms.
Uh, okay, we we heard enough about the
syllogisms, all right? You got anything
else you want to talk about? Yeah,
definitions
and what you define. What's the
definition of a definition?
And what's the definition of what you're
defining?
Okay, got it?
So, if you don't know that subject, you
can't go to chapter five. You're stuck
in four chapter, okay?
So, we have to do some background. I got
10 minutes left.
I'm going to give you some background on
sense and the people in the mixed nuts
translation group and the secondary
translators, uh they already
went through this suffering.
Each is so cool.
It's yoga suffering and
second school is suffering, okay?
You think first school is suffering,
second school is school is more
suffering, okay?
So,
I'm going to give you some background
right now, okay? And I'm going to go to
a different book.
And let me see, where is that?
Yeah, okay.
Let's go here.
All right.
I'm going to take this explanation
from a book
by
a llama called Ngawang Zangpo, okay? He
lived uh
300 years ago. You don't have to worry
about it, okay?
He's good. He's very, very good. He was
He went to the wrong monastery,
but
still he's good. I don't know what
happened.
He's from Drepung Monastery, okay? Dre-
Dre- There are three great monasteries
in the
Sakya tradition. They are Drepung, Sera,
and Ganden, okay?
Drepung means pile of rice.
Sera means uh hailstone.
Like snow like ice fall from the sky,
breaks things.
So, when we debate them in the
inter-monastic competition once a year,
we say that the ice broke the rice.
Said the ice broke the rice.
You know, Sera beat Drepung, okay? Then
they say, "Yeah, but then the ice melts,
doesn't it?
And the rice is still there."
Okay?
So,
he's from the wrong monastery, but it's
okay.
He's good. He's really good, okay? So,
here's his
discussion
of the definition of
definition, okay? What makes a good
definition? Okay? What makes a good
definition?
I'm going to give you the short
definition of a definition,
and then I'm going to give you the long
cuz you cannot appreciate the fifth
chapter unless I teach you something
about the definition of definition,
okay? Ready?
Definition
of a definition.
Zhe ya chos sum tsam. Zhe Say zhe ya.
Chos sum tsam.
Three qualities must be there. Three
qualities must be there. Chos sum tsam,
okay?
And they must be substantial.
Concrete.
You can touch it, you can feel it, you
can eat it. Substantial.
Okay?
They are real. What's the opposite of
like I don't know.
Substantial. What's the opposite?
We we say word in words only, in words
only.
Geshe-la, you want a yo-yo? Yeah.
I've been waiting. I've been hinting for
4 5 days.
No one gave me churro. No one gave me a
yo-yo. The ruskis didn't give me ponche.
Okay? I've been hinting over and over,
okay? I didn't get anything.
Okay? The ponche the the churro the
donut I got is a name only.
Okay? Say ta yo.
Just name. I keep talking donut donut
donut. But I can't eat words, okay?
That's called ta yo.
It's just words, okay? You can't eat it.
But it doesn't have any calories. That's
only good thing.
Okay? Ta yo. Ze yo. I want a ze yo
yo-yo.
Ze yo means
what? Real, substantial, okay? Real.
Okay? Ta yo means
You know, shopping keeps talking about
yo-yo, but I didn't get one. That's
called just talk talk talk yo-yo. Talk
talk talk yo-yo. So Geshe-la, no
calories. I don't care. I want the other
one.
That's the real one, the substantial.
Substantial one, okay? Okay? Understand?
Now.
And and we don't have time today to to
go all the way. We'll have to do some
tomorrow. But that's why I'm put giving
you a taste of the next chapter. I want
your mind to start thinking about it.
Okay? Now.
What's the definition of fire
in Buddha Buddhism? Tejas.
Something you put your hand next to it
and it feels hot.
And you touch it and you burn yourself.
That's the definition
of fire.
of fire, okay? Anything you start to put
your hand closer, closer, closer, it
feels warmer,
and finally it burns your finger, is the
Buddhist definition of the element of
fire, okay?
Okay?
So, the definition
is words or fire?
Words.
Right? I just told you, quote,
the definition of fire is hot and
burning, quote and quote, begin quote,
the definition of fire is
hot and burning.
And and and the definition, okay?
And then fire,
okay, in the kitchen,
the stove, put your finger in it, you
burn, okay?
Got it? Got the difference? Definition
is is the description
in English, in English. I don't know
about other languages. Definition is
Oh, somebody ask you, what's fire? Oh,
you know, it's a thing you put your hand
on it, you burn yourself. That's fire,
okay? That's a description in words,
right?
What we defined,
okay? Definiendum
in logic,
but I like to say
what we're defining, because definiendum
doesn't pass the
waiter test. If you order a definiendum
at the restaurant in Bowie,
I don't know what's going to happen.
But something bad, okay?
All right?
The thing you're defining
is the thing that burns you. Am I right?
I mean, it's fire, fire itself. So, the
definition is words.
Fire is
something burns you. So, here's a
question, my favorite
definition question.
Which is more
substantial?
The answer is the definition.
And it's confusing, okay?
And but you got to have this background
if I'm going to teach you the next
chapter. You need this background.
Because because Nagarjuna
attacks space
by discussing its definition.
And how does the definition apply to
space, okay?
Nagarjuna attacks the idea of space the
space
by looking at its definition, okay? Got
it?
And something you have to understand in
Buddhism
is that the definition is more real
than the thing you're defining.
And that needs some explanation, okay?
Here we go. After I tell you it won't be
confusing, okay?
Ready?
Uh
if I say
the definition of fire
is hot and burning
which hurts?
I'll give you three choices. Fire, hot,
or burning. Which one burns you?
The last two.
The word fire doesn't hurt you.
The hot and the burning hurts you. Which
is more substantial?
The hot and the burning. The definition
is more substantial
than what you're defining. Because what
you're defining is only a word.
What does
fire mean? Got it?
So really shopping's yocha is fire or
hot and burning?
Yeah, fire.
Just talk. No yocha.
Okay? It's not substantial.
Now, delicious and chewy.
Is that substantial?
Yeah, it's the definition of yocha, of
donut. Got it? Okay, so in Buddhism
we say the definition is more
substantial
than the word is defining, okay?
In In America, I don't know other
countries,
but we when we think about definition,
it's just words.
It's just words, but in Buddhism, now
listen, then we can stop the class. Yay!
In Buddhism,
the definition is the real qualities,
not the sentence.
Not the sentence. That's not the real
definition. The definition of something
is the qualities that define it. Got it?
So in In America, I don't know, in
English, when you say definition, and I
ask you, are you talking about a
sentence? They'll say yes. It's a
sentence that defines fire, okay? But in
Buddhism, when you say definition,
you're talking about the actual heat and
the actual burning.
Because those are the qualities that
make the fire a fire.
They define the fire. Got it?
So the the definition stuff is more real
than the fire, because the fire is just
a word until the definition is applied
to the fire. Got it?
Fire doesn't burn you. Hot and burning
burns you. Got it?
Cigarette doesn't burn you. The The hot
end of the cigarette burns you, okay?
Got it? The word doesn't burn you.
The The qualities that define the word
burn you. Got it? Okay.
Does fire burn you in this system.
No, the defining qualities of fire burn
you. We can call it a definition, okay?
That's what burns you, okay? Got it? You
have to know that
to study the next chapter because
here's the punchline, okay? Ready? Take
a deep breath. Put on your seatbelt.
Which came first, the definition or the
thing you're defining?
And we're going to do it next chapter.
Next clamp. That's the examination
of space.
Which came first?
The definition of space
or the space? Which came first? That's
the fifth chapter.
That's the fifth chapter.
I could say
this afternoon in your meditations and
tonight
don't think about monkeys. I could say
that.
But I'm going to say, don't think about
space
and the definition of space and which
came first.
Okay, don't think about that.
Cool?
Cool, ma? All right, let's go.
Although you got that mandala
man mundo.
Idam Guru Ratna Mandala Kam Di
Show me. Okay. Uh
thanks for being such good students.
Diamond Mountain has the best students.
I tell every city that.
Uh
but I really appreciate that you are so
hungry for such deep stuff. It's It's a
fun for me. It's much more fun for me
than repeating the pen over and over and
over and over.
All right.